翻譯：臉盆王子  牛奶器  小蠻腰
校對：蘇小黛
總監：somehacker
后期：Sung
如果你有發燒  咳嗽  喉嚨痛等癥狀
If you have a fever and cough or sore throat.
請留在家中
Stay home.
要我說這有95%的可能是實驗室搞出來的
I'd say 95% chance this is manufactured came out of a laboratory.
病源可追溯到
The source of the virus was traced back to
在舊金山創維實驗室所做的藥物檢測
drug testing done at gen-sys laboratories in San Francisco.
目前認定的首位感染者是實驗室技術人員
The lab technician now known as patient zero
他意外接觸到了ALZ-113逆轉錄酶病毒
was accidentally exposed to retrovirus alz-113,
這是種針對阿茲海默癥的試用藥物
an Alzheimer's trial drug
當時正用黑猩猩來做試驗
that was being tested on chimpanzees.
受到感染的黑猩猩
The infected chimps
表現出了不穩定性并伴有攻擊行為
showed signs of erratic and aggressive behavior
最終導致它們逃離了實驗室
that led to their escape from the facility.
金門大橋上的事件現在已經眾所周知
The now-famous incident on the golden gate bridge.
黑猩猩與警方對峙了6小時
A six-hour standoff with police.
最終消失在了紅木森林中
Ended with the apes disappearing into muir woods.
急診室已經不堪重負
Emergency rooms are being overwhelmed with
擠滿了出現"猿流感"征兆的患者
patients showing signs of what's being dubbed "The simian flu."
疾病控制中心預測
The CDC is projecting a fatality toll
未來六到八個月
ranging from 5 million
死亡人數將從五百萬增至一億五千萬
to as many as 150 million in the next 6 to 8 months.
出現感染癥狀的人都會得到特殊治療
Anyone showing signs of a contagious illness will receive special treatment here.
機場已專門建立了檢疫中心
The airport's purpose-built quarantine center.
許多新來者
Many of the new arrivals are
都是與父母失去聯系的孩子
children who have lost contact with their parents.
強制隔離措施引發了國內騷亂
The mandatory quarantines have sparked civil unrest.
很多家庭因此被拆散
Families are being ripped apart.
隔離不太可能有效
Containment is not very likely.
跟你的家人做好準備  熟悉逃生路線
Prepare your families. Know your evacuation route.
目前的存活率約為五百分之一
The survival rate is now approximately 1 in 500.
今晚在市中心發生了暴力沖突
Violence erupted in the city center tonight.
這已是這些天的來第三起暴力事件
The third incident in as many days.
已有28個國家宣布進入戒嚴狀態
Martial law has been declared in 28 nations,
包括美國和加拿大
including the U.S. And Canada.
核反應堆過熱  我們阻止不了它熔毀
The reactor is overheating. We can't stop a meltdown.
民眾秩序完全陷入了混亂
Just a total collapse of anything resembling civilian order.
由于猿流感肆虐成風
Due to the extremity of the simian flu crisis,
所有的政府職能部門都已無限期關閉
all regular government functions have been suspended indefinitely.
那些沒被病毒殺死的人
Those who aren't killed by the virus,
也許會死在斗爭中
will probably die in the fighting.
也許就這樣了
So, maybe this is it.
這就是結束
This is how it ends.
很快
Pretty soon,
人類就會滅絕了
there won't be anyone left.
猩球崛起2:黎明之戰
凱撒
Caesar.
它們在靠近
They are close.
科巴
Koba!
現在動手嗎  父親
Now, father?
兒子  別動
Son, stay.
謝謝  科巴
Thank you, koba.
兒子  要三思而后行
Think before you act, son.
別不開心了  藍瞳
Don't feel bad, Blue Eyes.
受傷能讓你變得更強
Scars make you strong.
過來看看你的弟弟
Come meet your new brother.
又一個兒子
Another son.
不禁感嘆我們已經走多久了  莫里斯
Makes me think how far we've come, Maurice.
貌似很久了
Seems long ago.
還會想他們嗎
Still think about them?
人類嗎
Humans?
有時候會
Sometimes.
我沒有像你那樣了解過他們
Didn't know them like you did.
我只看到他們壞的一面
Only saw their bad side.
好的  壞的  現在都不重要了
Good, bad. doesn't matter now.
人類自己毀滅了自己
Humans destroyed each other.
咱們也會打架啊
Apes fight too.
但咱們是一家人
But we are family.
真想知道他們是不是真的都不在了
Wonder if they're really all gone.
都過了10個冬天了
Ten winters now.
上兩個冬天就不見他們的蹤跡了
Last two, no sign of them.
他們肯定都不在了
They must be gone.
藍瞳  換我就不會被那熊傷到  我多快啊
That bear wouldn't get me, blue eyes. I'm quick!
閉嘴  噓
Shut up, ash!
天啊
Oh, God.
沒事的
It's okay.
沒事的  沒事的
It's okay. It's okay.
別動
Freeze!
Stay!
幫忙
Help!
快來幫忙
不許動
No!
在這里
Over here!
我打中他了  我打中他了
I shot him! I shot him.
他們打中了灰灰  他們打了我兒子
They shot ash! Shot my son!
火箭  先等等
Rocket, wait.
我們無意傷害你們
We don't mean any harm!
他們可是猩猩  怎么會聽懂你說什么
They're apes, man. You think they understand what you're saying?
你覺得他們只是普通猩猩嗎
Do they look like just apes to you?
爸爸
Dad.
馬爾科姆  你干什么
Malcolm, what are you doing?
-爸爸  -馬爾科姆
- Dad? - Malcolm.
沒事
It's okay.
把槍放下
Put your guns down.
-說什么呢  -放下
- You can't be serious. - Do it.
滾
Go!
天啊
Holy shit.
好的  我們馬上走
Okay. Okay, we're going.
滾
Go!
-慢點  -快走  走
- Slowly. - Go, go, go!
我的包
My bag!
快走
Go!
科巴
Koba!
跟著他們
Follow!
找到了嗎
Did you find it?
我們得談談
We need to talk.
怎么了  什么事
What? What's wrong?
水壩幾乎是完好的
The dam is pretty much intact.
估計一周內就能開始為我們提供能源
It could probably start generating power for us within a week.
但有個問題  上車再說
But there is a problem. Get in.
我打中他了
I shot him.
我很害怕  不知道該怎么做
I was scared. I didn't know what to do.
天啊  那里有多少只
Jesus Christ. How many were there?
很多  大概80只
A lot. Like, 80.
-至少80只  -好了
- At least. - Okay.
你都沒聽到他說什么  他們會說話
You're not hearing what he's saying. They spoke!
這不可能
That is not possible.
我跟你說  德雷福斯
I'm telling you, Dreyfus,
他們確實會說話  非常驚人
they did and it was incredible.
驚人  他們是會說話的猩猩
Incredible? They're talking apes!
-還他媽帶著長矛  -得了
- With big-ass Spears! - Please!
我不知道你認為自己看見或聽到了什么
I don't know exactly what you think you saw or heard,
但你得給我安靜下來  好嗎
but you have to calm down, okay?
病毒方面呢  埃莉  有任何進展嗎
What about the virus, Ellie? Any chance of contagion?
我們是因為基因免疫
We're all genetically immune,
不然早就死了
or we would've been dead a long time ago.
這你可不能確定
You don't know that for sure.
她是疾控中心的  她怎么不確定
She worked with the CDC. She knows.
我們怎么辦
What are we gonna do?
我不知道
I don't know.
我們需要那里的能源
We need that power.
他本可以殺死我們  但他沒有
He could've killed us, but he didn't.
也許他故意留我們小命  好跟蹤我們
Maybe he kept us alive, so they could follow us.
找到我們所在  再一舉殺光
They find out where we are, and they kill us all!
"他"是指誰
What do you mean, "He"?
這就是我們想告訴你的
That's what we're trying to tell you.
你絕對前所未見
It was unlike anything you've ever seen before,
他們的首領
and the leader...
絕對非同尋常
He was remarkable.
是嗎
Really?
-你是這么想的嗎  -這是我們看到的
- Is that what you thought? - It's what we saw.
沒錯  我們都看到的
Yeah, it's what we all saw.
回去不能再提及此事  懂嗎
Not a word of this back at the colony, you understand me?
在沒想出辦法前一句話也不能提
Not a word until we can figure out what to do.
-開什么玩笑  -我不是在開玩笑
- You gotta be kidding. - No, I'm not kidding.
我不想制造恐慌
I don't want to create a panic.
怎么樣  伙計  你還好吧
How are you doing, pal? Are you okay?
-我的包掉了  -我知道
- I dropped my bag. - I know.
-你的寫生本也在里邊嗎  -沒了
- Was your sketchbook in there? - It's gone.
卡弗剛跟我說
Carver just told me
不能跟任何人提起那里發生了什么
we're not gonna tell anybody what happened up there.
暫時先別說
Not yet. No.
我們必須現在就打過去
Must attack them now!
以防他們先動手
Before they attack us!
我們不知道他們有多少人
We don't know how many there are.
有多少槍
How many guns they have?
也不知道他們來這里干什么
Or why they came up here?
他們開槍打了你兒子  火箭
They shot your son, Rocket!
難道你不想報仇嗎
Don't you want to fight?
我聽凱撒的
I follow Caesar.
科巴說得沒錯
Koba's right!
他們差點殺了你  灰灰
They almost killed you, ash!
不
No!
如果挑起戰爭
If we go to war,
我們可能會失去這些年來建立的
we could lose all we've built...
家園
Home.
家人
Family.
未來
Future.
明早之前我會作出決定
I will decide by morning.
凱撒
Caesar.
多年來我一直被人類囚禁在實驗室
For years I was a prisoner in their lab.
他們拿我開刀
They cut me,
不斷地折磨我
tortured me.
是你救了我
You freed me.
我可以為你做任何事
I would do anything you ask.
但我們必須展示實力
But we must show strength!
我們會的  科巴
We will, koba.
借過  借過
Coming through. Coming through.
這他媽可遠不只80啊
That's a hell of a lot more than eighty!
馬爾科姆
Malcolm!
猿族
Apes
不想要戰爭
do not want war.
但若有必要
But will fight,
我們定將戰斗
if we must.
猿族的家
Ape home.
人類的家
Human home.
不要再過來
Do not come back.
各位
Everyone!
各位  你們得冷靜
Everyone, you have to calm down!
各位
Everybody.
所有人
Everybody!
請冷靜  我們都是免疫的
Please! We're all immune!
我們都免疫  不然也不會站在這里
We're all immune, or we wouldn't still be here!
他們怎么找到這的
How did they find us?
是我們先找到他們的
We found them.
你知道他們在哪里
You knew they were out there!
萬一他們回來怎么辦
What if they come back?
要是他們回來
If they come back, if they come back,
他們一定會后悔
they'll be sorry they ever did!
盡管現在這座城市的人口不復當年
Now, this city may not have the manpower it once did.
但它還擁有火力
But it has the firepower.
身后那批武器彈藥
Those stockpiles left behind.
聯邦應急管理局的  國民警衛隊的
By fema, the national guard,
現在都歸我們了
we have it all.
聽著
Look,
我知道你們為什么害怕
I know why you're scared.
相信我  我也害怕
I'm scared, too, believe me.
但我知道自己身上背負著你們的信任
But I recognize the trust you've all placed in me.
我們一起闖過鬼門關
We've been through hell together.
你們也都知道現在我們面臨著什么
But you all know what we're up against.
燃料快用完了
We're almost out of fuel.
這意味著提供不了電力
Which means no more power.
意味著我們要過回以前的苦日子
Which means we could slip back to the way things were.
而那邊的水壩就是解決方案
That dam up there was the answer.
只是我們沒想到他們也在那邊
We just had no idea they were up there, too.
那現在該怎么辦
So, what do we do now?
是啊
Yeah!
我們會想別的辦法
We find another way.
因為那里的電力
Because that power
不僅僅能使燈泡發光
is not just about keeping the lights on.
還能為我們提供工具
It's about giving us the tools,
與外面的世界重新取得聯系
to reconnect to the rest of the world,
找到外面的同伴
To find out who else is out there.
這樣我們就能開始重建
So that we can start to rebuild,
并且再造
and reclaim,
我們失去的世界
the world we lost.
講得不錯
That was a great speech.
但根本就沒有可替代的能源
There is no alternative power source.
水壩是我們的唯一選擇
That dam is the only option.
那只能跟他們拼了
Well, then, we fight them.
還有兩周燃料就用完了
We're two weeks away from running out of fuel.
最多能撐三周
Maybe three, tops.
我知道
I know.
燃料一旦用完
And once that happens,
我就不能再拿著個擴音器上去
I won't be able to go out there with a bullhorn,
指望他們平靜下來了
and calm everybody down.
我們需要電力讓無線電發射機重新運作
We need that power to get the radio transmitter working.
這是與外界取得聯系的唯一辦法
It's our only chance of reaching the outside world.
我們得找到其他幸存者
We have to find other survivors.
是啊  幸存者不多了
Yeah. There's not that many of us left.
不能再有人犧牲了
We can't afford any more casualties.
是我們找到了這個地方
We founded this place.
-我跟你  -我知道
- You and I. - I know.
靠能源才能讓我們回到從前的日子
On the idea that power would lead us back to the life we once had.
要是我們不團結  也許就活不下來了
If we can't stick together, maybe we can't survive.
我失去了一切
I lost everything.
一想到會再失去身邊僅有的...
The idea of losing what little I have is...
我想回到那里去
I want to go back up there.
聽我說  給我三天時間
Listen to me. Give me three days.
讓我跟他談
Let me talk to him.
行不通的話  再按你說的做
If it doesn't work, then we do it your way.
萬一適得其反  萬一他暴怒了呢
And what if it backfires? What if he gets violent?
你怎么知道他能明白你
I mean, how do you know that he'll even understand you?
他不僅僅是只黑猩猩
He's more than just an ape.
我要帶些人到尖兵堡
I'm gonna take some men up to fort point.
去軍械庫找找看
I'm gonna go through the armory.
看哪些還能用的
I'm gonna see what's still working.
三天
Three days.
要是你三天還沒回來
You're not back in three days,
我們就沖上去
we're going up there,
把他們殺到一只不剩
and we're gonna kill every last one of them.
卡弗正在備車
Carver is getting the trucks ready.
他跟福斯特還有肯普馬上就到
He'll be here with Foster and Kemp any minute.
真的要帶上卡弗嗎
You're really taking carver?
他可開槍打了他們
I mean, he shot one of them.
我也沒辦法
I don't really have any choice.
他在水利部門工作過
He used to work at the water department.
只有他知道怎么讓水壩運作起來
He's the only one who knows how the dam works.
馬爾科姆
Malcolm.
你去了打算怎么做  打算說什么
What are you gonna do up there? What are you gonna say?
我會跟他說實話
I'll tell him the truth.
希望趕上他心情好
Hope I catch him in a good mood.
你一定覺得我瘋了
You think I'm crazy.
我是擔心
I'm worried.
是啊  我也是
Yeah, so am I.
我仔細想了一遍
I've gone over it in my head,
要是我連試都不試
and I think if I don't at least try this,
那戰爭就真的無法避免了
there's gonna be a war.
把我也帶上
Take me with you.
有人受傷怎么辦  我可以幫忙
What if someone gets hurt? You'll need me there.
我愛你
I love you.
但我需要你留在這里
But I need you to stay here.
我不想留下亞歷山大一個人
I don't want Alexander to be alone.
我也去
I'm coming, too.
兒子  那里不安全
Son, it's not safe.
待在你身邊總比在這里安全
But I'm safer with you than I am down here.
我也去
I'm coming.
求你了
Please.
任何人都不許離開這輛車
No one gets out of the trucks.
任何人
No one.
要是我兩個小時還沒回來
If I'm not back in two hours,
你就帶他們回城
you get everyone back to the city.
不會有事的
It's gonna be okay.
拜托  拜托
Please. Please. Please.
請別殺我
Please don't kill me.
先聽我說
Just hear what I have to say.
我知道
I know.
"不要再回來"  我知道
"Don't come back." I know.
我來這里是因為...
I wouldn't be here unless it were...
好吧  好吧  好吧
Okay! Okay! Okay!
好  好  好
Okay, okay, okay.
我得帶你去一個地方
I need to show you something.
離這不遠
It's not far.
人類在撒謊
Human lies!
不  不
No! No!
不  不  不  我發誓
No, no, no. I swear.
去了你就明白了
If I could just show you, then you'll understand.
拜托了
Please.
帶路
Show me.
這就是人類所謂的"小型水電站"
This is what we used to call a "Small hydro".
本來是為這里以北的區域供電的
It was built to service areas to the north of here.
我們在試著把線路改裝向城市供電
But we've been working to reroute the power lines to the city.
城里核電站的能源
Because the city used to run off nuclear power,
幾年前就告竭了
but that ran out years ago.
這些年一直靠柴油發電機和氣化爐度日
So, we've been using diesel generators and gasifiers.
但要是能讓這個水壩重新發電
But if we can just get this dam working,
就可以將有限的化石能源貯存起來
then we have a shot at restoring limited power.
你能明白我的意思嗎
Is any of this making any sense to you?
燈光
The... lights.
是的
Yes.
燈光
The lights.
這是你的家園
This is your home.
我從沒想過將它奪走  真的
And I don't want to take it away from you, I promise.
但如果你允許我們在這里施工
But if you can allow us, let us do our work here...
你還帶了別人
You brought others?
就幾個人
Just a few.
我不會造成任何威脅
I'm not a threat.
不然的話
If I am,
你隨時可以殺了我
then I guess you can kill me.
不是吧
Come on!
等等  別慌  別慌
Wait, wait, wait! Stop, stop.
我們得把槍給他們
We need to give them our guns.
就這一個條件
That's the one condition.
什么意思
What does that mean?
我們能留下了
We can stay.
人類有了電力就會變得更危險
If they get power, they'll be more dangerous!
為什么要幫他們
Why help them?!
他們似乎已經走投無路了
They seem desperate.
如果趕走他們  以后一定會強攻過來
If we make them go, they'll attack.
來就來
Let them.
趁其疲弱  一舉消滅他們
We'll destroy them while they're weak.
有多少猿類得為此犧牲
And how many apes will die?
這是一個締造和平的機會
We have one chance for peace.
讓人類干完他們的活  他們就會離開
Let them do their human work. Then they'll go.
人類干的活
Human work?
Human work.
人類干的活
Human work!
科巴說
Koba say,
猿族應該憎恨人類
apes should hate humans...
夠了
Enough!
科巴在人類身上
From humans Koba learned hate,
只學到了仇恨
but nothing else.
你得吃點東西
Hey, you need to eat.
好  我只是
Okay, I just...
今天你的所作所為十分勇敢
That was brave, what you did today.
馬爾科姆
Malcolm.
我知道現在所有人都指望著你
I know everyone's depending on you...
我才不在乎  我一點也不在乎
I don't care about that. I don't care about any of that.
我只在乎他
I care about him.
他經歷的都不是小孩應該經歷的事
He saw things that no kid should see,
我不會讓情況再次惡化了
and I'm not letting us go back to that.
我知道
I know.
我也在試著消除和他的隔閡
I have been trying to get closer to him.
但
But...
總有一天會的
You will.
知道猿類可怕在哪兒嗎
You know the scary thing about them?
他們不需要電力  燈光
They don't need power, lights.
暖氣  什么都不需要
Heat. Nothing.
伙計
Hey, pal.
那是猿類的優勢
That's their advantage.
是他們比人類強大的原因
That's what makes them stronger.
馬爾科姆  今晚應該留一個人守夜
Malcolm, I'm thinking one of us should stand guard tonight.
拿什么守  槍都被繳了
With what? They took our guns.
他們要真動了殺心  咱們根本活不到現在
If they wanted us dead, we would be dead already.
他們可能只是不著急動手
Maybe they're just taking their time.
都已經干掉地球上一半的人了
They killed off half the planet already.
拜托
Come on.
怎么
What?
這真不能怪猿類
You can't honestly blame the apes.
那怪誰  本來就是猿流感
Who the hell else am I going to blame? It was the simian flu.
那也是實驗室里科學家創造出來的病毒
It was a virus created by scientists in a lab.
猩猩只是無辜的試驗對象
The chimps they were testing on didn't have a say in the matter.
別跟我扯大道理
Spare me the hippie-dippie bullshit.
你敢說你看到他們時
You're telling me you don't get sick to your stomach
不覺得惡心嗎
at the sight of them?
你以前不還有個女兒嗎
Didn't you have a little girl?
卡弗  夠了
Carver, that's enough.
-她是怎么死的  -夠了
- How did she die? - That's enough!
你老婆也是
Or your wife, for that matter.
卡弗  再不閉嘴我就要揍人了
Carver, you better shut up before I kick your ass.
好吧
Okay.
算我嘴賤
I'm the asshole.
沒事吧
Are you okay?
你聽起來生病了  還好嗎
You sound sick... you OK?
只是需要休息
Just need rest.
你操心人類的事就好
You worry about the humans.
科巴哪兒去了
Where's Koba?
生悶氣呢
Still angry.
他說要去打獵
Said he was going hunting.
看  下面有人類
Look, humans below!
我們來這干什么
Why are we here?
凱撒相信人類
Caesar trusts humans.
科巴可不信
Koba does not.
大多數武器應該還能用
Most of the arsenal seems functional.
好的
Good.
我們安排了人在那邊試射
We're testing them out back.
別動
Don't you move!
叫你別動  懂嗎
Don't move, do you understand me?
特里
Terry!
特里  快過來
Terry, get in here, quick!
我操
Holy shit.
怎么辦  怎么辦
What do we do? What do we do?
他從哪兒冒出來的
Where did he come from?
-要殺了他嗎  -我也不知道
- Should we shoot him? - Maybe. I don't know.
你還真他媽夠丑的啊
You are one ugly son of a bitch, aren't you?
悠著點
Whoa, man.
我想他應該是餓了
Dude, I think he's hungry.
一定是和別的猿類走散了
He must have gotten separated from the others.
你迷路了嗎
You lost?
要回家嗎
Trying to get home?
滾吧  離開這里  蠢猴子
Go on! Get out of here, stupid monkey!
快滾  照他說的做  快滾
Go on. You heard him. Go!
那些槍足夠殺死所有的猿類了
Enough guns here to kill every ape.
必須警告凱撒
Must warn Caesar.
天知道山上那些人在搞什么鬼
Who knows what humans are really doing up there?
堵住了  得炸開
We gotta clear this blockage.
我不知道你曾有個女兒
I didn't know you had a daughter.
是的
Yeah.
她叫什么
What was her name?
莎拉
Sarah.
我很遺憾
I'm really sorry.
現在有你和你父親陪著我  所以
Well, now I have you and your dad, so...
沒錯
Yeah.
-好了  -布置妥當了嗎
- All right. - You got all that straight?
引線就那么長了
That's all the wire we got.
注意安全
Brace yourselves.
三  二  一
Three, two, one.
-爸爸  -馬爾科姆
- Dad! - Malcolm!
馬爾科姆  馬爾科姆
Malcolm! Malcolm!
爸爸
Dad?
我看不到卡弗
I can't see Carver.
輕點
Don't!
-扶好了  -好的
- Leave it there. - I got it.
骨頭沒斷
It's not broken.
松開  好的
Let go. Good.
謝謝
Thank you.
你救了我們的命
You saved our lives.
我們得把那一大堆碎石給清理掉
We've got a lot of debris to clear now.
可能會耽擱久一點
We might need a bit more time.
多久
How long?
你好呀  小朋友
Hey, buddy.
干什么呢  弄好了嗎
What are you doing? Are you finished?
看什么看
What are you looking at?
從箱子里滾出去
Hey, get out of there!
-老子殺了你  -卡弗  你干什么
- Hey! I'll kill you! - Carver, what're you doing?
不要  不要
Don't! Don't!
凱撒  不
Caesar, no!
不要
No.
說過不準帶槍
Said no guns!
-不  別這樣  -拜托
- No, don't. - Please.
我并不知情
I didn't know.
人類  現在就走
Human leave now!
這下完蛋了
Man, we screwed now.
馬爾科姆
Malcolm?
馬爾科姆  你要去哪兒
Malcolm, where are you going?
馬爾科姆
Malcolm.
拜托  拜托  我得和他談談
Please, please, I just need to speak to him.
抱歉  都是我的錯  我會讓他離開的
I'm sorry. That was all my fault. But I will make him leave.
這是我的家
This my home.
你不該上這來
You should not be here.
我知道
I understand.
馬爾科姆
Malcolm.
她病了
She's sick.
她這樣多久了
How long has she been this way?
我帶了藥
I have medicine.
抗生素
Antibiotics.
也許她能幫上忙
Maybe she can help.
不信你
Do not trust you.
我能理解
I don't blame you.
但請相信我
But believe me.
我們并不都像他那樣
We are not all like him.
拜托  讓我們幫你吧
Please, let us help you.
一天
One day.
你們只能待一天
You stay one day.
父親  不行
Father, no!
-我們需要更多的時間  -就一天
- We might need more time. - One day!
猿族會提供幫助
Ape will help.
我才不幫忙呢
I will not help!
-你們瘋了吧  -把他帶走
- This is bullshit, man! - Get him out of here.
走  夠了  過來  離開這里
Move! That's enough. Come on, get out of here.
走吧  伙計
Come on, man.
行了吧
Okay?
給我過來
Move, come on!
上去
Get in!
明天見  混蛋
See you tomorrow, asshole.
剛從城市回來  人類十分危險
Just came from the city. Humans very dangerous!
凱撒在哪兒
Where is Caesar?
和人類在一起
With the humans.
亞歷克斯
Yo, Alex.
這個繼電器壞了  另外找一個來
This relay's busted. See if there's another one.
好
Yeah.
凱撒
Caesar.
不  不  不  別
No! No, no, no, don't!
不  不  不
No! No! No!
凱撒在哪兒  我要見他
Where Caesar? Want Caesar.
凱撒
Caesar!
人類攻擊了你的子民
Humans attack your sons.
你還讓他們留下
You let them stay!
置猿族于危險之中
Put apes in danger!
凱撒愛護人類卻不顧猿族
Caesar love humans more than apes!
不顧你的子民
More than your sons.
猿族
Ape...
不
Not...
殺
Kill...
同類
Ape.
原諒我
Forgive me.
你是我的孩子
You are my son.
我要你聽我說
I need you to listen.
你怎么不告訴凱撒人類試槍的事
You didn't tell Caesar about the guns we found?
你也不準說
Neither will you.
你父親不再信任我了
Your father doesn't trust me now.
你得保護他
You need to protect him.
他對人類的愛讓他變得盲目
His love for humans makes him blind.
我知道
I know.
只要人類還在這里
As long as they are here,
我就為凱撒的性命擔憂
I fear for Caesar's life.
昨天的事謝謝了
For yesterday.
看  看這兒
Look. Look.
看這兒
Watch.
這里
那是一個星期五
"It was Friday."
一個美妙的下午
"A real nice afternoon."
溫暖
"Warm."
我們外出
"We were hanging..."
我們外出郊游
"We were hanging out...
在水潭邊上開了一場啤酒聚會
"At this kegger down at the swimming hole."
外出郊游
Hanging out.
游玩
Hanging.
這里  你識字嗎
Here. You can read?
這可是好東西
Now, this is the good stuff.
-干杯  -干杯
- Cheers. - Cheers.
你到底有什么毛病
What the hell is wrong with you?
不是讓你滾回家嗎
I thought we told you to go home!
不
No!
不  走開
No! Go!
-他倒知道這個  -是啊
- He understood that, didn't he? - Yeah.
他好像喜歡你
I think he likes you.
得了吧
Shut up.
好吧  好吧
All right, all right.
想喝一杯嗎  丑八怪
You want a drink, fugly?
來  給他點
Go on, give him some.
給他點呀  伙計  看他什么反應
Give him some, man. See what happens.
給你
There you go.
我靠
Shit!
好喝吧
That's good, huh?
好了  好了
Okay. All right.
別激動
Easy.
是的
Yeah.
-別激動  -別激動
- Easy. - Easy.
好的
All right...
馬爾科姆
Malcolm!
怎么了  發生什么事了
What is it? What happened?
能用了
It worked.
至少在這里能用了
At least here it did.
城市那邊要等回去了才知道
We'll know when we get back to the city.
信任
Trust.
媽的
Son of a bitch.
真他媽能干
You son of a bitch!
燈光
The... lights.
好些了嗎
Feeling better?
母親
Mother...?
人類的槍
Human gun!
快逃
Run.
人類殺了凱撒
Humans kill Caesar!
燒了猿族的家園
Burn ape home!
上  抓住他們
Go! Get them!
猿族必須攻擊人類城市
Apes must attack human city!
回擊
Fight back!
來啊  為凱撒而戰
Come, fight for Caesar!
母猿和孩子留在這里
Females and young stay in woods
我們進城
we go to the city!
我們會為你父親報仇的
We will avenge your father's death!
埃莉  埃莉
Ellie! Ellie.
這里是舊金山發報點
This is San Francisco attempting contact.
如果有人收到這條信息
If anyone is receiving this message
請報上姓名和所在地  完畢
we ask that you identify yourself and your location. Over.
上  上
Move, move!
如果你收到這條信息
If you are receiving this signal,
請報上所在地  完畢
please state your location. Over.
重復  這里是舊金山發報點
Repeat. This is San Francisco attempting to establish contact.
如果你收到這條信息
If you are receiving this signal
請報上姓名和所在地  完畢
please state your identity and your location. Over.
出什么事了
What is it?
猿類襲擊了武器庫
The apes attacked the armory, sir.
拉響警報  拉響警報
Sound the alarm! Sound the alarm!
別讓它們上墻  別讓它們上墻
Keep them off the walls! Keep them off the walls!
快  各就各位
Let's go! Get into position.
-準備好了嗎  -好了  長官
- You ready? - Yes, sir.
很好
Good.
聽我說
Listen to me.
我們是幸存者
We are survivors!
雖然它們可能拿到了我們的一些武器
Now, they may have got their hands on some of our guns
但它們終究不是人類
but that does not make them men.
它們是動物
They are animals!
我們將擊退它們
We will push them back!
干掉他們
Drive them down!
它們別想進來
And they will not get through these doors!
那邊  加利福尼亞街
There! California street!
把火箭筒拿來
Bring me the rocket launcher!
我們的所在地有烽火標志
We have a beacon marking our location.
我們需要援助  我們遭到了襲擊
Please, we need help. We are under attack.
舊金山  重復
San Francisco. Repeat.
喂
Hello?
收到嗎
Do you copy?
人類跑了  抓住他們
Humans escaping! Capture them!
我們肯定快到了
We must be getting close.
我好像看到了  在這下面
I think I see it. It's down here!
爸
Dad!
天啊  馬爾科姆
Oh, my God. Malcolm!
埃莉  幫我一把
Ellie, help me.
我的
My...
兒子
son...
我的
My...
家人
family...
在哪
Where?
我不知道
I don't know.
別說話了  你需要休息
Try not to speak. You need to rest.
按住
Hold.
他失血過多
He's lost a lot of blood.
他能挺過去嗎
Is he going to make it?
我不明白
I don't understand.
卡弗是從哪弄來的槍
Where did Carver get the gun?
他為什么要這么做
Why would he do this?
猿族
Ape...
什么
What?
這是
Ape...
猿族
did...
干的
this.
上車
Get in the truck.
人類跑到這來了  到處躲藏
Followed the humans here. Hiding everywhere!
我們必須把他們都抓住
We must catch them all!
殺了他
Kill him.
不  不  不
No, no, no.
動手啊  灰灰
Go ahead, Ash.
讓人類付出代價
Make humans pay.
凱撒不會希望我們這么做的
Caesar wouldn't want this.
凱撒已經死了
Caesar gone.
猿族現在
Apes follow
聽科巴的
Koba now.
天啊  看  聚居地著火了
Oh, my God. Look, the colony's on fire.
我們接下來去哪
Where are we going to go?
凱撒  怎么了
Caesar, what?
是這里嗎  快到了嗎
Is this it? Are we close?
他要帶我們去哪
Where is he taking us?
馬爾科姆  停車
Malcolm, stop!
我不明白  我們來這干什么
I don't understand. What are we doing here?
無所謂了
It doesn't matter.
在我們搞清楚家里發生什么事前
We just need a place to hide him
得先找個地方把他藏起來
until we find out what's going on at home.
把桌子挪一下
Go move the table.
好了  就這吧
Okay. Right here.
好了
Okay.
爸  看
Dad, look.
看
Look.
我們得做手術  但我沒有工具
We need to operate. I don't have anything.
家里有手術箱  但那...
There's a surgical kit back at the place, but that's...
我去拿
I'll go.
那里不安全
It's not safe.
他是唯一能阻止這一切的人
He's the only one that can stop this.
人類
Humans!
你們現在是猿族的囚犯了
You ape prisoner now!
你們將嘗嘗生活在籠子里的滋味
You will know life in cage.
外面還有人類
More humans out there.
去  找到他們
Go! Find them!
莫里斯
Maurice...?
科巴說
Koba said
我們太忠于你父親了
we're too loyal to your father.
保護好自己
Protect yourself.
該死
Shit!
等一下
Hey, wait.
你父親
Your father.
他還活著
He's alive.
我拿到了
I got it.
他怎么樣了
How is he?
你母親
Your...mother.
弟弟
Brother.
都安全嗎
Safe?
暫時安全
For now.
不
No.
不是人類干的
Not human.
是科巴
Koba.
馬爾科姆
Malcolm.
開始吧
Yeah.
凱撒
Caesar.
我們得馬上開始了
We need to do this now.
兒子
Son.
他怎么樣了
How is he?
等等看吧
We'll see.
他很堅強
He's very strong.
不會有事的
It's gonna be okay.
我為這一切
I'm so sorry
向你道歉
for everything.
不
No.
這
I...
都是我的錯
am to blame.
但是科巴背叛了你
But Koba betrayed you.
我
I...
選擇了相信他
chose to trust him
因為他是猿族
because he is ape.
我一直認為
I always think
猿族比人類善良
ape better than human.
我現在明白了
I see now
我們有多么像人類
how much like them we are.
科巴現在在哪
Where Koba now?
在人類的塔上
On the human tower.
周圍有很多擁護者
Loyal apes around him.
那些不愿跟隨他的人呢
And those who not follow?
都成了階下囚
Prisoners.
莫里斯
Maurice.
火箭
Rocket.
科巴殺了灰灰
Koba killed Ash.
其他人也因為恐懼而服從了
Fear makes others follow.
但他們一旦看到你還活著
But when they see you alive
就不會再追隨科巴了
they will turn from Koba.
我這么虛弱可不行
Not if I am weak.
猿族只會追隨最強者
Ape always seek strongest branch.
我必須想辦法阻止他
I must do something to stop him.
父親
Father.
讓我幫你
Let me help you.
求求你們  放我們出去
Please, let us out of here!
好
Okay.
凱撒  看
Caesar, look.
蘋果
Apple.
很好
Good.
家
Home.
沒錯
Yes.
這是你的家
This is your home.
你的家
Your home.
很好  很好
Good. Good.
非常好
That's good.
對不起
Sorry.
我無意打擾
I didn't mean to intrude.
已經兩天了
It's been two days.
你兒子還沒回來嗎
Your son is not back yet?
那是誰
Who was that?
錄像里那個
On the video.
是個好人
A good man.
像你一樣
Like you.
他們必須偷偷上塔
They need to get to the tower without being seen.
我帶他走地下通道
I'm gonna take him through the subway.
我愛你
I love you.
科巴派人去接婦孺了
Koba sent for the females and young.
他們在來的路上了
They're on their way.
母親也會來
Mother too.
必須馬上走了
Must go. Now!
你沒事吧
Are you okay?
是誰
Who's there?
是人類就出聲
If you're human, you better say so!
是我  我是馬爾科姆
It's me! It's Malcolm!
別開槍
Don't shoot!
從樓梯上去
Take the stairs.
就能繞到街上去了
They'll bring you around and up under the street, okay?
去吧
Go.
謝謝
Thank you.
信任
Trust.
好了  我要出來了
All right, I'm coming out!
別開槍
Don't shoot!
看我找到誰了
Look who I found.
我都不知道你是否還活著
I didn't know if you'd made it out.
見到你真好
Good to see you.
別擔心
Don't worry.
我們會扭轉局面
We're gonna turn all this around.
什么意思  你們在干什么
What do you mean? What's going on?
猿類占領了塔樓
The apes. They're all over the tower.
信號丟失了  沒信號了
I lost the signal. It dropped out.
繼續試
Keep trying.
馬爾科姆  看這個
Malcolm, look at this.
C-4炸彈  每個五磅多
C-4. Five-pound blocks.
我們剛剛開始設置
We just started setting them.
這些炸彈將會炸跨整座塔樓
They're gonna take down the whole tower.
一下把他們全炸死
Blast them all at once.
你正好可以幫上忙
We could use your help.
這里是舊金山
This is San Francisco attempting contact.
如果有人收到
If anyone is receiving this
請報上姓名和所在地  完畢
we ask that you identify yourself and your location. Over.
給  快點
Here. Come on.
如果有人收到  請報上姓名
If anyone is receiving this, we ask that you identify yourself
和所在地  完畢
and your location. Over.
這里是舊金山
This is San Francisco attempting contact.
如果有人收到
If anyone is receiving this...
請報上姓名和所在地
we ask that you identify yourself and your location.
如果有人收到  請報上姓名
If anyone is receiving this, we ask that you identify yourself...
和所在地  完畢
and your location. Over.
德雷福斯
Dreyfus.
-有人聽到嗎  -維爾納
- Can anybody hear me? - Werner.
對不起  但我不能讓你們這么做
I'm sorry, but I can't let you do this.
我們必須給他個機會
We need to give him a chance.
我們得給他點時間
We need to give him some time.
他現在已經上去了
He's up there right now.
誰上去了
Who's up there?
這里現在沒凱撒的位置
Caesar has no place here.
猿族現在
Apes follow
追隨科巴
Koba now.
Follow Koba
將引發戰爭
to war.
猿族將贏得戰爭
Apes win war!
猿族團結起來力量大
Apes together strong!
凱撒
Caesar...
弱
weak.
科巴更弱
Koba weaker.
你他媽瘋了嗎
Are you out of your fucking mind?
不  我見過他們的生活
No, I've seen things. I've seen the way they are.
他們的目標跟我們一樣  只想求生存
They want what we want, to survive.
他們不想要戰爭
They don't want a war.
他們是動物
They're animals!
它們襲擊了我們
They attacked us!
因為他們以為我們襲擊在先
Because they thought we attacked them.
他們以為他死了  但他沒有
They think that he's dead, but he's not...
坐下  芬尼
Sit down, Finney!
坐下
Sit down!
我曾信任科巴如同兄弟
Trusted Koba like brother.
凱撒只把人類當兄弟
Caesar brother to human!
科巴為猿族而戰
Koba fight for ape!
解放猿族
Free ape!
是殺害猿族
Kill ape.
科巴是為自己而戰
Koba fight for Koba.
科巴
Koba
就該待在籠子里
belong in cage.
我知道這聽上去很瘋狂
I know how this must sound.
我覺得你沒明白
I don't think you have any...
你以為阻止我就有用了嗎
Do you think stopping me will matter?
他們要來了
They're coming.
我們聯系上了北部的一個軍事基地
Now, we made contact with a military base up north.
他們已經在路上了
They're already on their way!
是真的
It's true.
德雷福斯
Dreyfus!
你要干什么  伙計
What are you doing, man?
我要拯救人類
I'm saving the human race.
不
No!
猿族
Ape
不殺
not kill...
同類
ape.
你
You are...
不是猿類
not ape.
不
No!
放開他
Leave him!
你們在這不安全
You're not safe here.
他們建立了聯系  士兵要來了
They made contact. Other people are coming. Soldiers.
你們得馬上離開  所有人
You have to leave now. Everyone.
凱撒  如果你們不走  戰爭將全面展開
Caesar if you don't go, it'll be all-out war.
戰爭
War
已經
has already
開始了
begun.
猿族挑起了戰爭
Ape started war.
人類
And human...
人類不會寬恕
human will not forgive.
在戰爭開始前
You must go
你必須趕緊離開
before fighting begins.
對不起
I am sorry
朋友
my friend.
我還以為我們有機會
I thought we had a chance.
我也是
I did, too.